Preliminary Guide to the Paul Shepard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul Shepard papers
1860-1999
1939-1999
MS 1747
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
The papers consist of correspondence, research notes, drafts of writings, and published essays and book reviews by Paul Shepard. The papers also include reviews of Shepard's work, letters Shepard wrote to his parents during his military service in Europe during World War II and as a graduate student in the Conservation Program at Yale University, and letters from his friend and co-author Daniel McKinley. Other materials include grant proposals, genealogical files, personal papers, photographic slides, digital images, and legal materials.
Shepard, Paul, 1925-1996
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Florence Shepard, 1999-2002 and 2004.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Howe Shepard, Jr. received a Ph.D. from Yale University and taught natural philosophy and ecology at Pitzer College and Claremont Graduate School in California. His writings on the interrelationships between humans and the environment are provocative, literary, and mystical, as much as scientific. Shepard died in July 1996.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, research notes, drafts of writings, and published essays and book reviews by Paul Shepard. The papers also include reviews of Shepard's work, letters Shepard wrote to his parents during his military service in Europe during World War II and as a graduate student in the Conservation Program at Yale University, and letters from his friend and co-author Daniel McKinley. Other materials include grant proposals, genealogical files, personal papers, photographic slides, digital images, and legal materials.
Environmental sciences -- Philosophy; Human ecology; Nature -- Effect of human beings on; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American; McKinley, Daniel; Shepard, Paul, 1925-1996
- Inventory
  - Anthologies, 1959-1995 (Box 1)
  - Articles and essays, 1948-1997 (Box 2)
  - Reviews, 1952-1994 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-025
  - Reviews of Shepard's books, 1969-1999 (Box 1)
  - Green Oaks: A Memoir, 1955-1964 (Box 1)
  - Research on animals ads, undated (Box 1)
  - Research notes for New Zealand monograph, undated (Box 1)
  - Drafts, revisions for writings, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Student papers, 1948-1954 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2001-M-072
  - Publications (Box 1)
  - Unpublished writings (Box 1)
  - Book manuscript drafts (Box 1)
  - Writings, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with book publishers and agents (Box 1)
  - Resumes and brief biographies (Box 1)
  - Faculty appointments (Box 1)
  - Course materials (Box 2)
  - National Institute of Health Crow Study [includes motion picture film] (Box 2)
  - Illustrative material
    - English gardens, 1960s (Box 3)
    - Human/animal depictions (Box 3)
    - Thinking Animals (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1949 (Box 3)
  - Memorabilia, printed matter concerning the 12thArmored Division
    - General, 1945-1989 (Box 3)
    - Pictorial History of the 493rd Armored Field Artillery Battalion [edited by Paul H. Shepard], 1945 (Box 3)
    - Hellcat News, 1985-1990 (Box 3)
- Additional Material, 1946-1995; Accession 2002-M-099
  Scope and Contents
  This accession is composed entirely of correspondence.
  - A-C (Box 1)
  - Collier, John, 1956-1968 (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
  - Dufault, Peter, 1953-1995 (Box 1)
  - E-M (Box 1)
  - McKinley, Daniel [28 folders], 1948-1996 (Box 1)
  - Mountain Grove High School Class of 1943, 1989-1993 (Box 1)
  - N-P (Box 1)
  - Pitzer College, 1967-1982 (Box 1)
  - R-S (Box 1)
  - Sears, Paul, 1980-1995 (Box 1)
  - Shepard, Paul and Clara [3 folders], 1950-1979 (Box 1)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1978-1995 (Box 1)
  - T-W (Box 1)
  - Wood, Mal, 1946-1990 (Box 1)
  - X-Z (Box 1)
  - Yale University, 1976-1994 (Box 1)
  - Academic letters (Box 1)
  - Important letters (Box 1)
  - Military friends' letters, 1973-1988 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-010
  This accession is composed of teaching and research notes. The folder titles and order represent the materials as received from the donor. Abbreviations, spelling, and punctuation have not been changed.
  - Biology - History (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1)
  - Bibliog. (Box 1)
  - Play (Box 1)
  - Sleep & Dreaming (Box 1)
  - Ritual (Box 1)
  - Ontogeny & Ecology (Box 1)
  - Ontogeny [3 folders] (Box 1)
  - Cognitive Development & Culture (Box 1)
  - Developmental (Box 1)
  - Infant (Box 1)
  - Language Acquisition (Box 1)
  - Mid/Late Life Processes (Box 1)
  - Newborn (Box 1)
  - Fernandez (Box 1)
  - Childhood (Box 1)
  - Anti-Ecology (Box 1)
  - Body Percept (Box 1)
  - Adolescence (Box 1)
  - Neoteny (Box 1)
  - Children (Box 1)
  - Loose Ontogeny Notes (Box 1)
  - Nature Esthetics -- Pictures - (Box 1)
  - Eco-Philosophy (Box 1)
  - Pastoral & Romanticism (Box 1)
  - Travel (Box 1)
  - Backlash/Media (Box 1)
  - Built Space (Box 1)
  - Catastrophe Course (Box 1)
  - Tropical Ecology (Box 1)
  - Planet Evolution (Box 1)
  - ES 30 Fall >84 (Box 1)
  - Env. & Genetics JSS (Box 1)
  - Ethics & Theology (Box 1)
  - Technochracy (Box 1)
  - Ideology (Box 1)
  - Deep Ecology (Box 1)
  - Evolution & Ethics (Box 1)
  - Machine (Box 1)
  - Natural Theology (Box 1)
  - Technophilia (Box 1)
  - Midwest (Box 1)
  - Courtly Love/Naturalism (Box 1)
  - Gardens (Box 1)
  - Hindus (Box 1)
  - Feminist Ecology (Box 1)
  - Africa (Box 1)
  - Environmental Ethics (Box 1)
  - Biosphere (Box 1)
  - Nature-Hating Documents (Box 2)
  - Nature Esthetics: - Landscape (Box 2)
  - Eco Philosophy (Box 2)
  - Nature-Hating as Subject (Box 2)
  - Schneidau (Box 2)
  - Gary (Box 2)
  - Campbell (Box 2)
  - Arboreal Cycle (Box 2)
  - Speech - Cognition (Box 2)
  - Pedagogy - Writing (Box 2)
  - Catastrophy (Box 2)
  - Goddess (Box 2)
  - Maternal Epiphany (Box 2)
  - Paternal Epiphany (Box 2)
  - Sexual Dimorphism (Box 2)
  - Organicism To be filed with ES 30 (Box 2)
  - Ecology of Phytogenesis (Box 2)
  - Psychopathology (Box 2)
  - Psychiatry (Box 2)
  - Env. Ethics & Philosophy (Box 2)
  - Agricul. Origins (Box 2)
  - Agric. History (Box 2)
  - Desert (Box 2)
  - Agric. Ethos (Box 2)
  - Domestication (Box 2)
  - Irrigation - Agriculture (Box 2)
  - Christians For Nature (Box 2)
  - Mesopotamia (Box 2)
  - Pastorality Edgerton (Box 2)
  - Peasants (Box 2)
  - Watershed (Box 2)
  - Bible Chronology (Box 2)
  - Christianity (Box 2)
  - Ancient Greece (Box 2)
  - Greeks (Box 2)
  - Hebrews (Box 2)
  - Messiahs & Kingdoms (Box 2)
  - Middle East Hist. (Box 2)
  - Mythic Mind (Box 2)
  - Paradise (Box 2)
  - Protestant (Box 2)
  - Unfoldered pages (Box 3)
  - Searles (Box 3)
  - Hominids (Box 3)
  - Steiner (Box 3)
  - Bernard Smith (Box 3)
  - Nabakov (Box 3)
  - Berman (Box 3)
  - W. Berry (Box 3)
  - Eliade, Micea (Box 3)
  - Fernandez (Box 3)
  - Hardin, G. (Box 3)
  - Henderson (Box 3)
  - Paul Winter (Box 3)
  - Abram (Box 3)
  - Levi-Strauss [2 folders] (Box 3)
  - Population/Ethology (Box 3)
  - Shamans (Box 3)
  - Martin, C. (Box 3)
  - Neo-Cynegetics Food Technology (Box 3)
  - Primitives (Box 3)
  - Hominids & Hunting (Box 3)
  - Cynegetics - Tools (Box 3)
  - Lee, Richard (Box 3)
  - Cynegetics - Exercise (Box 3)
  - Density & Behavior (Box 3)
  - Food (Box 3)
  - Paleolithic Hunters (Box 3)
  - Totemic Thought (3) III. Identity (Box 3)
  - Living Hunters - Reprints (Box 3)
  - Hunting - Evol. & Ecol. (Box 3)
  - CHD Clarke (Box 3)
  - Hunting (Box 3)
  - Neo-Cynegetics (Box 3)
  - Levi-Straus (Box 3)
  - Language Evolution (Box 3)
  - Contemporary Hunters (Box 3)
  - Socio Biology (Box 3)
  - Gronbech [empty folder] (Box 3)
  - Attention & Intelligence (2) (Box 3)
  - Pleistocene (Box 3)
  - Cynegetics (Box 3)
  - Hunting/Gathering (Box 3)
  - Marshack, A. [empty folder] (Box 3)
  - Clippings [empty folder] (Box 3)
  - Ecol & Way of Life (Box 3)
  - Paleolithic (Box 3)
  - Hunting (Box 3)
  - Cynegetics (Box 3)
  - Ecology & Intelligence (Box 3)
  - Primitivism (Box 3)
  - Children [empty folder] (Box 3)
  - Pre-History of Consciousness (Box 3)
  - Paleolithic Art & Religion (Box 3)
  - Meeker (Box 4)
  - Chas. Lindbergh (Box 4)
  - Yale (Box 4)
  - White (Box 4)
  - Lorenz (Box 4)
  - Modell (Box 4)
  - Lowenthal (Box 4)
  - Leopold (Box 4)
  - Romanticism (Box 4)
  - Ontogeny Issue Landscape and Urban Planning (Box 4)
  - Constructing A World (Box 4)
  - Erickson Ontogeny (Box 4)
  - Child & Mother (Box 4)
  - Children & Nature Univ. Utah (Box 4)
  - Youth (Box 4)
  - Mechanism (Box 4)
  - Misc. Notes (Box 4)
  - Ambiguity (Box 4)
  - Ambiguous Animals (8) I, III, VII Cognition, Identity, Otherness (Box 4)
  - American Indian (Box 4)
  - Apes (Box 4)
  - Attention (Box 4)
  - Biosphere (Box 4)
  - Birds (19) (Box 4)
  - Categorization (Box 4)
  - Commodity (27) (Box 4)
  - Celtic Alternative (Box 4)
  - Cognition Taxonomy (Box 4)
  - Cosmos (Box 4)
  - Disappointment (Box 4)
  - Duality & Control (Box 4)
  - Esthetics & Mechanism (Box 4)
  - Dreams & Pictures (4) VI Exemplary (Box 4)
  - Domination of Nature (Box 4)
  - Ecology (Box 4)
  - Environmentalism History (Box 4)
  - Gimbutas (Box 4)
  - Horses (Box 4)
  - Humanism (Box 4)
  - Linearity (Box 4)
  - Luria (Box 4)
  - Masks & Demonology (Box 4)
  - Masks & Music (Box 4)
  - Mediator (Box 4)
  - Medieval (Box 4)
  - Membership (Box 4)
  - Nature-Hating Notes (Box 4)
  - Naturalism - Ecology (Box 4)
  - Perception (Box 4)
  - Pesticides (Box 4)
  - Protection (Box 4)
  - Social Criticism (25) VII Others (Box 4)
  - Spine & Dreams (Box 4)
  - Simulations (Box 4)
  - Simians & Prosimians (Box 4)
  - Snake & Fish (17) (Box 4)
  - Story (Box 4)
  - Sublime (Box 4)
  - Social Identity (9) III Identity (Box 4)
  - Therapy (28) VII Others (Box 4)
  - Zoology of the Self (7) III Identity (Box 4)
  - Transformation (Box 4)
  - Vision (Box 4)
  - Valve (Box 4)
  - Watching (Box 4)
  - Woman & Nature (Box 4)
  - Willis (Box 4)
  - Journals - Papers (Box 4)
  - A-B-C [divider followed by loose pages] (Box 4)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-086
  This accession is composedof research notes, manuscripts, personal papers, genealogical files, legal records, and images. The folder titles and order represent the materials as received from the donor. Abbreviations, spelling, and punctuation have not been changed.
  - Photographs [2 digital discs], Before 1945 (Box 1)
  - Memorial for Parents, 1990s (Box 1)
  - Yale Records/Awards, 1950-1954 (Box 1)
  - Wheatcroft-Shepard Marriage, 1950 (Box 1)
  - University of Missouri, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Misc. Records, Colleges, 1949-1966 (Box 1)
  - Military Records, 1942-1946 (Box 1)
  - Mountain Grove/School PHS Jr. (Box 1)
  - Certificates- Birth, Baptism, Death, 1925-1996 (Box 1)
  - Employment Applications (Box 1)
  - Yachts (Box 1)
  - Travel/Immunization Registers (Box 1)
  - Thoughts and Messages during terminal illness (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Tributes (Box 1)
  - Pitzer- 5 Year Review (Box 1)
  - Honors/Organizations (Box 1)
  - Resume (Box 1)
  - Yale Alumni, July 1969 (Box 1)
  - Corres. - Ecstasy (Box 1)
  - Intros. MIL (Box 1)
  - Written or Edited for Clara Shepard by Paul Shepard (Box 1)
  - Syllabi (Box 1)
  - Proposals, grants, studies
    - Visiting Scholar University of Melbourne, Australia, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Pitzer Studies of Artemis, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: FIPSI, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Fulbright Myths and Legends of Peru, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: NCCAT, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Large Scale Nest Cavity Restoration, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Fulbright Indonesian Study, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Distinguished Fulbright Professor - India, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Scripps/Pitzer, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Bear Study, 1983 (Box 1)
    - C.I.E.S. - Indo-American Fellowships, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Charles Lindberg Fund, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Nature of Place, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Proposal: Exploring Env. Values Dartmouth, 1973 (Box 1)
    - NIH Crow Study Proposal, Papers, Notes, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Olympic Park Controversy, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Research
    - Hudson River Paintings (Box 1)
    - New England History Notes- (Box 1)
    - American West (Box 1)
    - Oregon Trail - Notes on Journals of travelers Coe (Box 1)
    - Oregon Trail [slides] (Box 1)
    - American South (Box 1)
    - English Gardens Study [pamphlets] (Box 1)
    - Environmental Correspondence and Permissions, 1971 (Box 1)
    - New England Art. - Notes (Box 1)
  - Genealogy
    - John Shepard - Civil War Journal, 1860s (Box 1)
    - Family Names and Places (Box 1)
    - Notes on Ancestors by Paul Shepard (Box 1)
    - Genealogy - General Info (Box 1)
    - Paul Shepard's Notes on Ancestors (Box 1)
    - Shepard Reunion Big Spring State Park, MO, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Lineage Charts (Box 1)
    - Coat of Arms - Shepard (Box 1)
    - Copely Family (Box 1)
    - John Shepard - Civil War veteran pension letters, 1870s - 1880s (Box 1)
    - Perce Shepard Misc. letters (Box 1)
    - General William Shepard (Box 1)
    - Morse family (Box 1)
    - Capt. Roger Clap (Box 1)
    - Carlton Morse Shepard (Box 1)
    - Gerald Faulkner Shepard (Box 1)
    - John Howe (Box 1)
    - Robert Augur (Box 1)
    - Phelps family (Box 1)
    - Pond family (Box 1)
    - John Strong (Box 1)
    - Faith Shepard Wolpe - DAR application (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Grigsby Line (Box 1)
    - Grigsby Genealogy (Box 1)
    - M.G.H.S. 50-year Reunion Memory Book, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Program/Speech Notices (Box 2)
  - Additions - Conferences (Box 2)
  - Travel Journals (Box 2)
  - Additions - Publications (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - Additions (Box 2)
  - Reviews - Additions (Box 2)
  - Letters from Paul Shepard, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Huth, Hans - Original letter (Box 2)
  - Delorenzo, Teresa Int'l Bear News (Box 2)
  - How It Feels to Be a Walking Stick, 1968 (Box 2)
  - About Paul Shepard (Box 2)
  - Oregon Trail (Box 2)
  - Permissions - Paintings, 1953-1956 (Box 2)
  - Permissions - Sub. Sci, 1967 (Box 2)
  - New England Geology - Agriculture - Notes, 1950s (Box 2)
  - The Panther News Mountain Grove H.S. Paper Paul Shepard - Editor (Box 2)
  - Pre- Man in the Landscape ?? (Box 2)
  - [An essay per day], 1960s-1970s (Box 2)
  - Farrar Straus and G. Contract The Others (Box 2)
  - Hellcats 12th Armored Division [WWII Memory Book], 1940s (Box 2)
  - Man in the Landscape [First Draft], 1957 (Box 2)
  - Legal papers concerning Sanders v. Shepard, 1983, 1990-1995 (Box 3)